so a couple of suitors maybe
on a similar theme it's the
sangeeta Nick and Sally at another sense
senses 153 bhikkhus there is a method
153 bhikkhus there is a method
sorry no yes yeah he asks the monks
bhikkhus is there a method by means of
which bhiku from a place other than
faith other than preference other than
tradition other than and examination of
properties other than relying upon and
the insight from a view just examination
of the properties yeah it's basically
psychologizing it is isn't it that's how
I basically it's hard to transfer it
translating these terms
yeah so but I sort of miss thinking
about it's exactly like just examining
fraud just informing yourself about a
property observing the properties of the
thing yeah
you mistake for understanding the nature
of the thing yeah this is nature of
basically the core of circle area it's
our car parry bit significant so like
thinking about the arc era which could
be that what makes the thing he was made
of was made of the properties qualities
its components he's component area
analysis well yeah yeah so
so from a place other than those is
there a method by means of which a
bhikkhu might describe final knowledge
thus I understand that birth is
destroyed the how black has been lived
what should be done has been done
there's no more of this and the bhikkhus
say I don't know you tell us yes there
is he then says and which bhikkhus is
the method by means of which a bhikkhu
from a place other than faith so on
might describe final knowledge thus I
understand birth is destroyed and so on
so he says here bhikkhus the bhikkhu
having seen a sight with the eye
when there is passion aversion
distraction internally he understands
for me there is passion aversion
destruction internally
that that passion aversion distraction
is just compound word
so these different thing not these
different things to draw this past
relationship destruction rocket there's
some basis of animals they rip yeah in
another place like the roots of the
unhealthy so having seen when there is
fashion version displays destruction
internally he understands for me there
is passion aversion destruction
internally when there isn't passion
aversion destruction internally he
understands for me there isn't he
understand do you understand
there isn't this he's clear and by the
way when we speak when you say the
necessary basis for things that's what a
root is a root is a necessary basis for
the existence of a tree the root doesn't
disappear once the trunk starts to grow
yeah you need to be there throughout and you
you need to be there throughout and you
can have the trunk disappear you know
the root mister but if the root
disappears the trunk cannot remain
little so the roots of the adults the
root of their whole necessary basis for
involvement so whenever you read about the root in
so whenever you read about the root in
the Sutra that's what it means necessary
basis for this understanding the
necessary basis for greed and lust and a
cerebus for aversion for distraction
and you'll see probably later I guess
but based on what that suit is going not
understanding what necessary basis is is
what provides the necessary basis for
these things yeah understanding the mind
with greed aversion delusion
he's already step closer to overcoming
the greed aversion delusion yeah it's
simple simply once once as past aversion
distraction if those the necessary basis
for the wholesomeness is there how do
you know it's there and see so that's
the method yeah method is not to looking
in the front of you notice apologize not
to be examining the properties or just
adhering to it blindly because the
tradition told you so yeah or the
authority of the teacher told you so the
method is to discern the background
peripherally what state of mind you are
in while this is happening to me in the
front yeah so by seeing sight with the
eye instead of hmm what did I see what
is it made of where it came from how it
came to be how does it affect me all of
that is in the front all that is rooted
in you not seeing the State of Mind
simultaneously present with that sight
on account of that side so sure yeah
there is a method which is completely
opposite direction of any notion of
method people might have who's usually
method is methodical analysis I mean
performance but know as a word method is
absolutely fine it's just what people do
in a counter better now there's nothing
wrong with it with a word in itself we
return yeah it is this is a formal
method as well but a method that you
cannot observe psychologize measure ya
or decide beforehand I think yeah so
basically so it's something is somewhere
other than faith
that's not to say the faith is
necessarily a bad thing no no no but
faith is there in the front yeah you
place faithful things right in order to
start practicing whatever so it is
necessary in that sense but it's a way
so Tamar has a different faith cannot
arrive at this it's a not faith not
preference no preference I've done this
side over there tradition or away from
words doing it because just what your
nostrils just did pay attention to that
so this examination of properties
analysis psychologizing scientific
quantification Oh everything is
constantly changing just explaining
everything nicely neatly from relying on
insight from of you but I say that well
I think that's it something like well
that's I can get in this new Gianna the
insight review and the result is sort of
you know exactly I think being like
having some kind of understanding based
upon of you yeah which is applying to
what's in front so so you're extending
the principle that you get from your
view yes as in you're not seeing it
directly yes you're just sort of if this
is the case here so it's to this extent
because that's have you understood the
case in front of it yeah which means
yeah you can be holding on to a view and
because of that not seeing you can't say
to the mind because you're
reinterpreting it from the point of view
yeah it should have an account of it
which kind of makes it again implying
that external template exactly template
that has been created or a kind of some
inside of some view yeah right or wrong
doesn't matter yeah I mean by the way
even the right way works the same way
you create the right template so to
speak that's one our hunt is beyond the
view beyond the template yeah he has
fulfilled the template yeah
the brothers words and loving-kindness
and a fog analyst 15 and a programmer
it's not having not going into a view
not not wrong views or fixed views yeah
not still depending on view day so
so he says he asks the customers
viki's for a bhikkhu happiness in who
has seen a sight with the eye for whom
this passion aversion distraction
internally and to understands for me
there is passion perversion distraction
internally wall for a bhikkhu having
seen you've seen a side of the eye for
whom there isn't passion aversion
distractions I mean who understands for
me there isn't passion privation
distraction internally bhikkhus are
these things to be known by me into the
faith absolutely not how they do know
how they to be known by means of
tradition by an examination of
properties its amounts all of that
they've been tired the rain released of
these things are blinded it can only be
known directly right here right now or
are they say no bhikkhus he says oh
these things to be known having seen
them with understanding
this bhikkhus is the method by means of
which a bhikkhu from a place other than
a condition etc might describe final
knowledge
so the method is to know the background
of your method
okay faith of the observances some of
your analysis of your traditional
techniques if you know the background of
it you're going to be on the method and
yeah you can call that the right method
because it cannot it can only be seen
from the standing which means seeing it
means understanding oh yeah
and understanding and understanding
those dispassion yeah understanding not
just not just so understanding what
exactly what it says
not understanding the contents of this
particular let's not understanding
that's you examining the properties and
then kind of classifying and collecting
them you know understanding what
understanding what state of mind is
simultaneously present with this
simultaneously during sight what state
of mind is simultaneously present with
this simultaneous enduring feeling is it
the state of mind with passion is it the
state of mind free profession know that
to its extent means you're getting to
know the nature of the phenomenon that
your mind is and if there is passion
the version distraction there you know
with this onion you see it so not kind
of or now I need to cite in else yeah no
no you need to know it to the extent
that it is because the problem is not in
in those thoughts that the problem is
not even in that mind so to speak the
problem is you not understanding its
extent yeah so you like to go to close
too far trying to go overly affirm it
already denied you get involved you get
burdened by the whole thing
and then it becomes your passion your
everything you because why because
you're acting out of it
and you certainly it's not a matter of
choice that's another preference to just
choose to okay I will not have these
states of mind because they aren't also
with us can you obtain these things by
by preference no means you can't choose
your way out of it yeah but if you know
the state of mind within the present
enduring choice to what site to its
feeling towards whatever that's how you
step outside of but that's not something
you can look at directly which will be a
matter of choice a matter of examination
that's impossible discerning the proper
route yeah the proper necessary basis which is
yeah the proper necessary basis which is
always very far from where you look
because normally that's really should
not reach would be me yeah yeah exactly
that's the assuming it's the default but
the point is see the sight sound smell
taste touch it's always in front of you
it's always the perception or it has to
be in front and this is not in front
yeah and you could see that's where all
these things have in common they're also
in front examination preference just do
this so I just have clarity of
information what needs to be done pull
passed down to me by tradition by
requirement and I'll do it over
limestone in the front and so where the
sense is up yet the real method is
actually completely the opposite
direction defined by what's not in front
you can't see your mind on the level of
the site but the last is not in the side
it's in the mind yet all you keep to
keep doing in order to get through the
last in mind is examining the sites
that's why you are unsuccessful man if
you like things manipulating preventing
controlling denying indulging all these
were three bolts against it completely
misplaced because you don't know that
there is simultaneously present enduring
root of that significance of the whole
site and everything that's pressuring
you bothering you exciting you whatever
whichever site it is the necessary root
is the state of mind effectively loss on
the state of mind
effectively last so you need to train
that peripheral vision you cannot like
find a way they would then enable you to
look at it directly and okay now I'm
done
to pick up the sign pick up the sign of
your mind the necessary condition for
the rising or flood right here
become familiar with the sign of your
mind sign with of the phenomenon of the mind
sign with of the phenomenon of the mind
for what it is see for as long as you
assume that you can observe your mind on
the level of the senses with a method of
observation means you don't know what
the nature of the mind is with with your
you don't know it's science
that's what I always like when we're
doing the those previous interrogations
like what is the current mood I feel
because that's already a background of
whatever you're doing now trying to
understand now I want to say now I want
to deal with him now you're in a certain
mood that's where you start looking for
your mind in the direction where your
mood is and that's not something you can
put in front of it because you
performing effort openly something front
is on the basis of that within that
container of that move the entire life
of the tree is contained within the
existence of the roots functioning roots
present roots doesn't matter how big the
tree get its life is always within the
basis of this because if that disappears
none of the extent of the tree can
remain the the
different suit
so this the this root root of the
unwholesome
and go to a book of threes
but it says there are these three
grounds for the arising of action which
three
Noba so I'm going to translate his
desire is in the ground for the arising
of action
perversion is a ground for the arising
of action ignorant
it's a ground arising back
whatever action is done with desire born
of desire grounded and desire arisen out
of desire
wherever self existence is born there
that action bears fruit wherever that
action bears fruit their one experience
is the results of that actions either in
this life but we've been reborn in some
other way arising in some other way
the eruptions done with version that
we've done with ignorance
or collusion distraction born of
ignorance grounded in ignorance there is
no difference wherever self existence is
born there faction relations whatever
that wherever that action ripens their
one expert is the result of an action
he's in this very life or having arisen
in some other way
suppose because some seeds that were not
broken not rotten not spoiled by wind
and heat taken from the most excellent
part well embedded made in the good
ground were laid in the ground in well
prepared earth and the sky would provide
the right amount of rain
these seeds between the bakeries room
the go and increased growth abundance in
just this way degrees whatever actions
done with desire diversion
diversion
ignorance forever self-existence cool
there that's actually ripens wherever
that actual ripens and their one
experience as a result of an action
either in this very life or
they're just these the idea of these the
roof and necessary basis action
this isn't gonna cut it well it kind of
sounds pretty much straightforward yeah
whenever you choose to act you will do
so how you feel so you can other well
you can say them it is that is for
foreign unlike mine that is only one
basis of action action by bodies future
mind that basis is craving towards
feeling which of these rigs yeah greed
which can be raving through green agent
bathing through a virgin craving through
distraction what it is is basically your
response to feeling yes attitude your
attitude towards the feeling that you've
been subjected to yeah pleasant
unpleasant or neither unpleasant no
present and that's the and that there
cannot be any other action on the level
of comma it will have its ripening as
the Buddha described it unless it's
rooted in that so in other words if you
learn how to act without being rooted in
craving you will be another vent so that
and that's why there does not constitute
the action on the level of karma and
vipaka because there is no training it's
not done by him for him for others it's
yeah because that the whole domain is
gone domain that six it's been existing
when I can't agree the version delusion
being there so that's that the second
part of the Super sisters think there's
these three grounds of the arising of
action which three non design non desire
non-efficient non aversion knowledge
whenever in action whatever actually is
done with non desire for all of Norma's
I grant in non design there isn't
Houston on design being without desire
in this way that action is abandoned the
top of the Ruiz made like a so whatever
action is done without craving it's not
an action anymore yeah the action is
abundant so its internal state of mind
determines whether you act or not not
what you do externally it can be done
observed by others
yeah there's certain things that you
cannot do once the craving is gone their
sexual intercourse actually kill
somebody lie and things like that but
many other things can be done by both by
not hunting by precision digging body
they both walk talk choose prefer yeah
but one is action the other one isn't
because one is rooted in craving how he
feels at the time the other one it's not
rooted in that because he doesn't feel
anything anymore so the roots of the
action for the arahant is yes the
necessary basis places and but it's not
really action yeah exactly
like in other words if you decide to
call it an action show but then you need
to understand it's not the action of two
Gina yeah it's not the same action today
because there's the Buddha describes one
results in this whole nice of suffering
righted right now or even later or both
the other one is cut of its root right
there and then because he hasn't been
done by Claire is never Parker there's
no result from this sorry
it's not an action exactly so that's a
minute if you were to learn how can you
act without needing to crave and desire
the action you'll be enough what you'll
be at least a sort of honor if you then
develop that type of action you would be
an automatic and that's what we spoke
before like you know see you think your
act only when you're kind of aware of
what you want to do but even now while
we're talking my hands are moving my
feet changed position all of these
things so the body keeps acting in its
own domain and it's only got space but
you regard that as secondary to my
action that I choose to voluntarily
volitionally perform its other way
around the only reason you can choose
and perform things with extra layer of
volition is because the body allows you
to which means the domain of this random
movements of the body breathing shifting
changing posture standing up going to a
toilet eating all of that that is on its
own and those are already actions they
don't require craving to be done so
you're all right you're all you're doing
when you are intention angles put my
hand in the air now you're basically
bringing awareness to this whole domain
of stuff is there any way yeah well
you're not the creator of any of that
yeah you have within it yeah so your
volition is secondary to the domain
where you can exercise it but it's
usually my volition is the center of the
action and these are all its results in
the repercussions so rooting
all those actions that are going on
already yeah so that's that's the policy people
yeah so that's that's the policy people
don't if people can't differential is
that's when you start to blame
everything and nothing yeah oh I need to
move I can't move my leg I can't do this
I can't do that because that's craving
that's craving that's good
I don't have this cells responses in
action and that's already something a
fully do it yeah so it's more like no no
it's all around so all these things are
done they don't need the craving yeah so
let me just make a point then when I'm
aware that I'm acting acclaiming not do
that and then let the body do what he
wants to do yeah you cannot accidentally
have a sexual interest yeah you cannot
accidentally kill somebody what if you
gently kill somebody it's not a murder
it's an accident so I'm referring to is
like to volitionally performing these
actions which is why I required this
kind of a certain perpetuation of the
level of craving desire for action and
that's why the extent of it cannot be
done by another hand he doesn't have
that at all so it talks about greed
aversion distraction so it's simply
restraint starting point and see this
another interesting thing here is that
how I said by not understanding this you
put your volition first you think that's
the root and then you try to sort of
even practice the Dharma through that
and by that I mean you become aware that
the body has its own domain but it does
all these things you don't need to keep
thinking about all these little
movements postures scratching but now
you realize but I must be aware of
everything so but instead of seeing in
your volition is secondary and by
understanding the right order you become
aware of it you try to then sort of
subjugate everything to your volition
and that's when you get the repast and
the techniques of oh I can't just be
aware of my obvious desires and cravings
I must be volitionally aware of setting
setting moving to
King touching touching leaving just not
just shouldn't just be aware the fact
I'm walking but I must keep raising my
bullish rising the bullish to bring I
missed a bit then yeah exactly
failing to see that what you're doing is
actually trying to force practice Adama
through the wrong good yeah it should
fit yourself and that's why it doesn't
matter how much volitional you commit to
it you're committing to your wrong view
of what comes first but instead you need
to recognize that all this lifting
putting setting resisting scratching is
done by the body on that level so just
don't lose the corner of your eye you
don't need to tend to it and that's the
point by becoming familiar with the
actions that don't need your attending
your volition you becoming familiar with
the actions they don't require craving
and then you can relax because you know
all I need to do is stay the gate in
case the craving comes if it's not I
have no I don't need to stop in search
everyone because that's not the point
the point is I know what the craving is
there when the aversion is there when
the desire for distraction is there
that's what I don't act on it and that
is always as I said before in previous
talks that is always intentional
you cannot unintentionally choose a
desire it's always implies awareness of
that choice which means you're always
responsible for choosing desire a
version and distraction so instead of
trying to override everything with your
completely misconceived volition you
have to start including the volition a
secondary to all these little things
that you actually do throughout a day
and you just need to remain aware of
them peripherally just know that it's
being done not specifically to what
extent and how fast I'm moving my life
the body oh that's why dead body
postures at the gentle like general
reference points doesn't matter what I
do now as long as I keep a corner of the
eye that this body this lump of flesh is
seated whatever is done has to be done within
whatever is done has to be done within
that posture
now I have a choice to get up to change
the question that's a volitional choice
but even that can eventually become
normal there's a need to stand up I'll stand up
there's a need to stand up I'll stand up
I don't need to always attend to it so
instead of trying to override everything
with your volition start including
basically a relation is second to
everything the only reason you can
choose you can will things is because
there is a body in its own domain
performing all these things anyway
anyhow and then you add an extra layer of I
and then you add an extra layer of I
want this sublet and that extra layer is
completely gratuitous leave rooted in
desire of original distraction
which you put first and there is no
beginning of that as the Buddha said a
major ignorance of that principle is
beginningless so yes this cannot be
first it shouldn't be firstly not
knowing that you put it first and there
is no first point when that mistake
manifests there that is your starting
point there is your resistance which is
why it's irreversible once you undo it
once you become an arahant you cannot
reverse the picture and go back to the
owner of petitioner because it's
impossible for that order to be now
knowing that that's how you place it it
fills out we have a lot to say